Guide to the Benajah Ticknor Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Journals, Series I
  Ticknor devotes quite a few pages to his own opinions on the celebrated Parkman-Webster murder trial. Dr. Webster had chopped up Dr. Parkman, his creditor. In most histories the case is given as an example of how flaming passions and sordid crimes could be hidden behind a Brahmin name. Ticknor's comments, however, emphasize the legal and philosophical morals of the case. One of Webster's defenses was that he could not be executed for first-degree murder since the crime he had committed was an act of passion or temporary insanity. Ticknor dismissed such a plea since, to him, if one's passions gained the upper hand, then it was because one had allowed them to do so, and in allowing or consenting to the dominion of one's passions over one's natural reason, one in a sense designs and plans that the act of passion should happen; therefore, the crime is premeditated, and the charge should be murder. Ticknor's view of original sin, and, since this thinking was incorporated in the state's case and Chief Justice Shaw's charge to the jury, Ticknor's tedious remarks on the subject show the effects of the old moral philosophy of New England in one of its final and most spectacular phases.
  The last remaining item of interest in Journal VI is Ticknor's first, last, and only meeting with his celebrated cousin, George Ticknor, the publisher and literary scholar who promoted the cause of Germanic scholarship in America. Benajah suspected that the erudite and wealthy cousin would look down on his country cousins from Connecticut. Benajah was agreeably surprised when George seemed quite interested in the western branch of the family, and Benajah had to admit that, despite his wealth and genteel interests, George Ticknor was an "all right" fellow.
  Journal VII (1851-1852) describes the last years of Ticknor's service as Chief Surgeon at the Boston Navy Yard. The bulk of this unbound volume is devoted to family news, remarks on intemperance, and a trip to Michigan, where Ticknor himself was involved in another lawsuit which was decided against him. In 1852 he heard rumors that he was about to be assigned to a naval station on the coast of Africa but instead he received ordem to act as surgeon at the annual naval rendezvous at Boston. The Ticknor Journals end here.
  - Journal, Vol. I -A, pp. 1-46, 1818 -1821 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. I -B, pp. 90-223, 1818 -1821 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. I -C, pp. 224-281, 1818 -1821 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. II -A, pp. 1-270, 1831-1833 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. II -B, pp.271-539, 1831 -1833 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. II -C, pp. 888-1030, 1831 -1833 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. II -A & B revision with some narrative missing on Siam between Vol.II - B & C, 250 pp., 1831 -1833 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. III, 115 pp., 1837 April - November (Box 2, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Journal, Vol. IV, 374 pp., 1838 -1842 (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 2U)
  - Journal, Vol. V, 278 pp., 1845 -1848 (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 2U)
  - Journal, Vol. VI, 312 pp., 1845 -1850 (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 2U)
  - Journal, Vol. VII, 112 pp., 1851 -1852 (Box 2, Folder 12, Reel 2U)
- General Subject file, Series II
  This series is divided into two major categories, the letterbook, 1844-52 and Writings.
  Letterbook, 1844-1852
  The letters in Ticknor's 1etterbook mainly concern health reports to his superior officers, correspondence, letters to the Navy Department, and pension certificates for naval personnel, 1844-1852. Some of the letters are from Ticknor to his lawyers concerning his lawsuit against the Ohio Stage Coach Company in 1849. The letterbook is prefaced with a table of contents, there is also an index pertaining to people and subjects in the letters. The Index list seem to have been compiled by Donald J. Warner, the donor of this collection and the grandson of Benajah Ticknor.
  Writings
  This subseries contains an essay on remarks concerning religious establishments. Though Ticknor's views on temperance, wealth, dancing, and the Sabbath are quite similar to the views held by Congregationalists of the period, he was in fact an Episcopalian. This essay attempts to show that the established Episcopal Church in England is not so bad as that of the Catholics and that the establishment of the Episcopal Church in America would have distinct benefits. The manuscript is dated October, 1835, from Boston
  Also in writing is Ticknor's analysis of "The State of Religion in America". A great deal of his remarks bemoan the decline of the religious energies of the nation through sectarianism and misplaced zeal of the major sects in getting new members rather than in promoting true religious feelings. He examines the Methodists, Baptists, Congregationalists, Presbyterians, and Episcopalians and the divisions within each group which have allowed religious apathy to flourish and which have allowed the Catholics to take over missionary work in the American West. In this regard Ticknor criticizes Lyman Beecher's "Pleas for the West" which was of course violently anti-Catholic. Ticknor says the meager state of Protestant missions in the West is due more to internal divisions than to the eternal pressure of the Catholics. The essay does provide some hints of two coincident but apparently unrelated events in the mid-1830's: the rise of Transcendentalism with its revolt against the older religious sects and the anti-Catholic agitation in Massachusetts. The essay is also unique, because, though written in Boston in 1835, it ignores almost completely the influence of the Unitarians.
  The essay entitled "Mammon Punished", dated 1842, in New York is Ticknor's attempt to explain the causes of the great depression which began in 1837 and continued until the Mexican War. His essay is divided into four parts. The first three examine the successive roles of the Bank of the United States, private merchants, and corporations as causes of the depression. Ticknor's conclusion is that none of these elements were the real causes of the depression but, rather, the true cause lay in America's inordinate, greedy thirst after things of this world and that the depression was a just punishment of this materialistic spirit. The concluding part of this remarkable essay on religious economics is Ticknor's exhortation for America to rediscover true religion and enjoy the riches of the spiritual world.
  The remaining foldetsare mainly medical notes and random pages from unknown sources.
  - Index to Letterbook of official letters & reports, 1844 May 21-1854 April (Box 3, Folder 13, Reel 3U)
  - Letterbook: copies of official letters and reports sent while a surgeon of the U. S. Navy, 196 pp., 1844 - 1854 (Box 3, Folder 14, Reel 3U)
  - Writings
    - Diseases, an imcomplete essay on diseases, pp. 51-54, 131-134 (Box 3, Folder 15, Reel 3U)
    - Education, an incomplete essay on education. pp. 97-100,105-108 (Box 3, Folder 16, Reel 3U)
    - Mammon Punished, 187 pp. (Box 3, Folder 17, Reel 3U)
    - Medical Symptoms and Cook's History of the Reformation, noted on, 27pp., undated (Box 3, Folder 18, Reel 3U)
    - Murders, Suicides, Executions, list. of 6 pp., 1835 -1836 (Box 3, Folder 19, Reel 3U)
    - Naval discipline, incomplete remarks on, 8 pp., undated (Box 3, Folder 20, Reel 3U)
    - Observations on Physiology and Pathology (Cures),190 pp., undated (Box 3, Folder 21, Reel 3U)
    - Quotations on Music, Woman, Luxury, etc., 23 pp., undated (Box 3, Folder 22, Reel 3U)
    - Religious Establishments, 178 pp., 1835 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
    - Self-Indulgence, incomplete essay on, 43 pp., undated (Box 3, Folder 24, Reel 3U)
    - State of Religion in the United States, 88 pp., 1835 (Box 3, Folder 25, Reel 3U)
    - U.S.S. Peacock: General Health Report, 3 pp., 1832 -1833 (Box 3, Folder 26, Reel 3U)